agentic analytics or basically anything
using AI, you're moving on more of a conversation pace, Right?
I mean, you have a conversation and you ask me a question, I take ten minutes.
I just think about it and say it's not a very good conversation.
your pipelines will probably error out and your waste tokens, things like this.
So you want a subsecond kind of response for this stuff to work.
Oh, no. Oh!
Okay.
Hi everybody.
I'm here to talk about data harnesses, so I've gone with a belabored pun
billion, but I'm going to talk about getting data
optimized and efficient and delivered it in a way that really helps
whatever you're doing, whether it's engineering,
which will talk about later, or analytics, which is kind of
more Dremio in my area of expertise.
So my name is Will Martin.
I'm the data and AI evangelist at Dremio.
I started out doing statistical analysis
at the Large Hadron Collider, and since then I've spent about 15 years
in the data industry doing pretty much every role that starts with the word data.
So I've been a scientist, engineer, consultant, analyst,
and now I am specifically the data and AI evangelist.
And most recently I wrote
the book Agentic AI for Dummies.
In terms of, I hear you ask, who are they?
So we call ourselves the lake house provider.
We are a lake house provider, much like these more familiar logos here on screen.
But there is one key difference between them and us.
We have the better mascot.
His name is Gnarly.
He's very cute and much easier to personalize for blogs and events.
Talking of cute logos and cute mascots, we also have this guy here.
Is anyone familiar with this?
You can see, correct?
Yes. So.
Yeah.
Yes, we based it.
He's got a little Scottish hat.
I don't know the word for it.
It's arguable if he ever existed at all.
Nessie in particular.
But this is the mascot, the logo for an open source data catalog.
And Dremio created it, which not a lot of people make that connection.
Other open source logos we are associated with
are these two Apache Arrow and Apache Polaris.
So while we do sell a data lake house, we heavily invest in open source standards.
So these three projects in particular we have Apache Arrow back in 2016,
which was co-founded by the same people who founded in the same year,
which is a crazy popular in-memory format
and now a transport format for processing columnar data.
So great for analytics.
There's a little stat there, 100 million plus downloads per month.
That is specifically just the Python library implementation.
Just pi Arrow.
For some reason they don't track the other libraries, but a stats
are pretty crazy that in 2017 Apache Iceberg came out.
We did not create this in any way, but we're big educators and users of this
ways.
We contribute as I go and talk about it, and then we have engineers on staff
who develop the code and contribute to the project.
And then most recently we have Apache Polaris.
So this is another metadata catalog similar to Nessie.
And we launched this in 2024 with Snowflake.
And originally it was meant for Iceberg metadata
only if you're familiar with that.
But now it does other stuff. In particular it does Delta.
So if you want an open source Delta Lake catalog,
this is a great thing to go for rather than something like Glue.
And to prove the educational aspects.
We wrote the book on Apache Iceberg for O'Reilly,
and we wrote the book on Polaris as well.
So who here is familiar with data?
Lake houses
should be a lot of people, but there's a little distinction.
It gets confused with lakes quite a lot.
So data warehouses are great for analyzing data,
but they're a little painful for storing because of costs.
And if your size goes up, your cost goes up quite a lot.
So data lakes came along, which are great for storage,
but the painful for analytics.
The idea was to do the best of both worlds and bring them together.
So Lake plus house from warehouse is Lake house.
It's as simple as that.
No idea is to combine the two together and you get the strengths of both.
So you've got the low cost, scalable storage of say, S3 or something like this,
but you've got reliable asset transactions
you would only typically get in a warehouse.
So you have this kind of layout here.
You've got your lake, and your computers would be a kind of data lake layout.
To turn this into a lake house, you had two components.
You've got a metadata catalog, which provides the right version of your data
set from your lake to your compute.
And then you have a metadata format, also known as a table format.
And this is metadata about your data defines
things such as your schema, your history, things like this.
It's great for rollback, great for just
getting around kind of issues with Parquet,
which you may get in an analytic space, especially a fast moving analytic space.
So a general layout looks like this.
Really you have Iceberg data in some kind of lake variety of catalogs.
You can be using, variety of engines you can be using.
So a data lake house is made in quite
the same way you would make it in real life.
Lake house. You find yourself a data lake.
You add a little bit of structure in terms of a catalog and submitted data,
and you have yourself a lake house.
So a typical data lake, well, a general data lake house platform looks like this.
You have your your file format for storing your data in.
You have your metadata format for storing your metadata.
You have a catalog.
And this acts as a kind of middleman and sends the right information.
You want to look at to your compute, which will be a query engine.
So for me we look like this.
We write data in Parquet because it's columns and columns are fast.
We use Iceberg.
It's the only format we use.
We've been using it for a long time.
And now every other lakehouse in this space is using it, including Databricks.
We have our own open catalog, which is powered by Apache Polaris,
and we have our own query engine which uses Apache Arrow.
So on the right you can see
the OSS talk isn't a bunch of marketing.
We actually invest in it and we use it in every part of our stack
because it's really performant and it's good to use.
And there's other benefits, which I'll talk about shortly.
Okay.
So what's this actually got to do with the topic of today?
We're talking about harness engineering.
So typical layouts.
If you're not using a lake house you typically got something like a lake
here you've got some sort of data silos or your data in different places.
Maybe it's another database, maybe a catalog,
some object storage, God forbid, in Excel.
Or you may be using a warehouse.
So the old fashioned kind of analytics space.
So legacy analytics a couple of years ago you were kind of moving at an email base.
So you'd write a query
and it would take minutes to ours was was seen as acceptable.
Right.
So like you're emailing a colleague, they'll get back to you.
Shortly hopefully that within the day.
And that's fine for people right.
That's fine. It will work with this.
It works if your data silos
and you're pipelining at around definitely works for a warehouse,
but for a
genetic analytics or basically anything using AI,
you're moving on more of a conversation pace, right?
Even if you exclude sort of chat interfaces.
Right?
I mean, you have a conversation and you ask me a question, I take ten minutes.
I just think about it and say
it's not a very good conversation. Right.
And your pipelines will probably error out and your waste tokens, things like this.
So you want a subsecond kind of response for this stuff to work.
And it's not really I want really it's a requirement.
Right.
You need this kind of speed because if you're working
in the old style stuff takes minutes or hours for a person, that's fine.
I'll go make a cup of tea.
I'll come back, but it's not going to work for agents.
So things like a lake, a lake in particular isn't going to cut it
for this kind of work.
So today I'm going to talk a
little bit about making a quality data foundation
and a platform that kind of delivers this to whatever your needs are.
So whether you're doing analytics or you're doing engineering,
the needs are very similar.
You data needs to be accessible to be able to see your whole data estate
so you can get the right
well need to see all the information so you get the full picture.
So any assessments or analytics or anything you build is accurate.
It needs to be understandable by whatever's accessing it.
So you don't have to ask people you know what the data means
and it needs to be performant. Right.
You need this conversational pace.
And I'm going to put forward that.
The modern data Lake House does this and all counts.
And it also uses it with open source standards.
So you're not locked into any vendor.
You will see a few specific features.
I've put a little Gnarly there so you know what they are,
but I'm mostly not going to talk about them because I'm not here to sell you a.
But this is what Romeo looks like.
This is the full platform.
So your data layers at the bottom layer, whether it's object storage.
So you're kind of lake or any other kind of system.
You've got warehouses, catalogs, you name it, you've got your execution layer.
And at the top you've got the things that are actually using it.
But of course we're talking about AI. So I've scrubbed
by off all of these slides because it's not relevant.
But starting with AI, right.
Whether you're doing engineering or analytics, you're connecting stuff to AI.
We integrate three ways.
We have an agent built in if you don't want to build anything.
So a big thing for analytics is the push for democratization of data.
It was Databricks is slogan for quite a while, and this is for people
who don't want to build and just what he use.
They don't have to do anything.
It's just a tab in the UI.
There's the model context protocol, which everybody uses again open source.
So fantastic.
And you've got to develop a CLI.
So if you're doing
more programmatic stuff doing stuff for terminal you've got this.
So the full breadth of how you want to connect
your data estate to an AI, whatever you want to do it.
You have it from very business focused, evade technical focused.
And I think for you, everyone here in this room, it's
probably these two on the right that are more relevant,
but it doesn't really matter.
Right?
It's just we connect to AI but like it doesn't matter if you integrate,
if what you're integrating with isn't very good.
So the focus of the talk is this execution layer.
So the things inside that make the lake house the query engine,
the semantic layer and the open catalog.
So and together these form the performance data harness.
So really help you do your work with AI.
So the catalog straight up.
So we have the Dremio Open Catalog I call the open catalog
because Snowflake also have an open catalog.
It is also powered by Apache Polaris.
I'm not sure why we all decided to do that.
It's a little confusing, but the idea here is Polaris
is a great open source project.
It became came out of incubation in February this year
and delivers all of these great features you would want from a data catalog.
And on top of that we add a few things.
We have something like
Iceberg clustering, which is a nice alternative to partitioning.
So what happens here is you cluster up similar values in your rows.
You cluster your rose by similar values,
but you're not splitting up your data into partitions, physical partitions.
So you get improved read performance.
And it's a bit more easy to sort of understand and and
get your head around, especially for business users, which is a lot of people.
We go towards your table maintenance features such as garbage
collection and compaction, things that are essential for a lake house.
And everybody does.
I'll talk a bit more about them later.
And then there's also role
based access controls, which is part of essential governance.
If you're doing this kind of thing, you can restrict what people are looking
at based on roles or even down to the very fine grained level rows and columns.
So optimization
is a very common across the industry, whatever lakehouse you're using.
So there's a thing called the small file problem.
I'm sure probably anybody a lot of people here have heard about it.
If your data comes in and it's in lots of files, these files
take a while to open and it makes stuff slow and expensive to do.
So you want all your stuff in one big file that makes things more performant.
And that's what it is.
It just smooches things together into more compact files.
Vacuuming gets rid of unused metadata, sort of from failed attempts
or things you're not really using anymore, gets cleaned up and save you storage.
And then you have something called variant shredding, which is a bit more recent.
So is anybody familiar with Apache Iceberg or uses it?
Okay, so with V3 evade the modern spec for Iceberg.
There's a new data type included called variant.
And this basically puts semi-structured data into a cell of your table.
So this is something that's been in Delta Lake for a long time.
It's been added to Iceberg. And in fact it's been added to Parquet.
So anything that runs off Parquet, any metadata format can use this part
of the the secret sauce for why Iceberg and table formats and lake houses
are so performant is because of something called predicate pushdown.
You know, if you're looking for certain values, say you're looking at
software developers age 20 to 35.
The metadata knows which files and which partitions,
including those files, have the data you're looking for.
But if you're shoving JSON into a cell,
you can't pull that information out until you have variant shredding.
So this is a way of pulling out
this nested or sort of compressed or structured information out of a cell,
so you can efficiently only open the partitions
that contain the data you need and in the files you need.
It's what make things quick.
And then the catalog
also gives you end to end access control.
So both thing is governance giving your users.
And likewise any AI or AI agents access to the right information.
And it can do it at every level.
So Polaris provides credential vending for the major hyperscalers.
So you get storage level access to anything inside your storage,
and it goes all the way along to column and row level access
through masking and filtering.
So you can really tune stuff down specifically to
to any kind of user.
And likewise the agents are doing their work for them
or the agents you are training or the agents
you are developing or the are you working with.
Okay.
Second, sandwiched in between, we have the AI semantic layer.
The AI isn't really too essential here.
It's not too different than what it's always been.
But the idea is really that terms of subjective, right?
So many, many business terms are not universal.
If you talk to one company and then talk to another company,
what they call a customer isn't necessarily the same.
And then things that include money, I have to be calculated on the metrics,
like revenue in particular is very different company to company.
Then you get stuff like this, which if you've been a consultant
or an analyst like me, you've seen a lot, right?
I've got over 15 years experience.
I have no idea what this is unless I talk to somebody.
Claude's not going to be any better.
It's trained on a lot of data, but it's not trained specifically
on a company's data.
So yeah, these
definitions vary a lot, and you are lucky if your company just has one.
So if you talk to, say, your customer support team, their view of what
a customer is, their definition is going to be very different to your sales team.
And a lot of times these definitions aren't even in your tool, right?
They're downstream quite a lot of the times, a lot of times
in by tools or separate spreadsheets, data dictionaries, things like this, things
where your AI or any kind of downstream tool isn't really looking.
Having it separate from your data is not a good idea.
So you have no definitions.
You're just going to guess.
I would guess your model will guess with confidence
and then anything you get out of the process,
any kind of analytics or anything you've engineered and built,
you're going to have to question and drill down
and figure out what you're actually looking at,
what definition you were using, and if you have multiple definitions,
it's pretty much the same, right?
You just got to you're going to pick one
thing, you're going to argue over whether you pick the right thing and
you still can't trust what you've got.
It's the same problem.
So really you need to consolidate your context into a single layer,
a semantic layer, if you will, and put it in your platform.
It just makes things simpler.
You're connecting whatever system you've got downstream for your AI use cases.
It's far nicer just to connect to one place,
keep your data and your metadata together.
And just write down what a column actually means,
what a metric is defined as, and then how your tables relate
and how which is really easy in a lot of places are doing
because a lot of tables are defined as SQL, right?
It defines how you derive a gold layer data set from a silver layer.
It's right there in in the SQL.
And actually just source of truth.
So you can ask your agent whatever question you like.
So we have a question here
which is laden with a bunch of very specific business terms.
Q2 you would think isn't too different from one company to another,
but we've just been bought by SAP and our Q2 is are very different
to each other.
So it varies within a company.
But you can see this as your prompt.
You're asking your agent your prompts.
It breaks it down to tasks.
And with a semantic layer it can reliably take action.
So it can go and find metric definitions which are defined in one place.
It knows what your sales table is compared to the others
because they're named properly or identified or tagged.
And they can explain what the table means
because it knows what the column definitions are.
So this can be anything from very simple things such as a label,
which is like just tagging your data set as something to a wiki
to have a more elaborate stuff like knowledge glow offs.
I think there's a lot of consolidation in the industry,
and talk about standardizing a lot of the semantic layer.
You've probably heard of OSI, which is the Open Semantic Interchange.
So this was launched
last year with a couple of companies like Salesforce and Snowflake.
It has recently turned into an Apache Software Foundation project called OSI.
The logo is a kangaroo.
It's not very cute.
It hasn't got a face, but the idea there is to standardize
how to share semantic information between tools.
But in terms of the implementation within tools, it can vary quite a lot.
Still, we'll see what happens as as the space develops.
Okay, that's 2 to 3 features.
The last component is the query engine.
So does data Federation.
So hands up if you were born in the 90s
okay.
So we've been talking about tearing down data silos as long as you've been alive.
But they are still around and for good reason.
People have kind of given up now on trying to tear them down.
They're there for a reason.
Data goes in and data comes out.
So they are kind of painful to get rid of.
So Federation's the way it's at.
So like with a lake house where you're querying the data,
where it lives, query your data, where it lives in these other systems.
So data federation, you can support multiple table formats
thanks to something like Apache Polaris.
Other data catalogs thanks to something I'll talk about shortly.
Object storage, databases, you name it.
The idea is to get the data accessible from one location,
so centralized your access and your governance, but not physically
centralizing your data because that's the trap warehouses fell into.
That's the pain point there.
Down here we have reflections.
This is a custom query acceleration feature
which I won't talk about, but we do do caching.
A lot of people do caching.
We have query plan caching.
So if you're writing data queries
your query is the same but your data is changed.
You can just use the same query plan halves the amount of work you're doing.
Likewise, we have results sets that are saved.
So if you're running the same query, the query is the same,
the data is the same.
Just give you back the same results.
And then the custom side we have Columnar Cloud Cache
we always struggle with what to call it — I prefer C3.
The idea here is we just put data.
You frequently look at the access and we store that in the storage.
It's on your clusters on your nodes and it sits right next to the compute.
So for some customers you're getting like costs dropped by 90%.
There's something really basic right.
We're just using stuff that's not being used.
So that's the performance data harness.
Then we have the open data harness.
I've talked about open software a bit.
So a little bit more is these bits are kind of grayed out.
So for us in particular we we have our own query engine.
It's very performant.
It's fun to use. Well funds a strong word.
But there's other things on the market too.
There's Kafka, there's open source stuff like Spark.
And likewise we support other query engines.
So things like Snowflake, Athena, Trino, open source Fabric, very much
not so, but
we permit full read and write access to the data catalog
and the underlying storage, which is unique in the market.
And we do this because we're using open standards.
Right.
So at the beginning I showed this as other sort of general layout of Dremio.
I just moved it left a little bit.
So this is the dream Lakehouse platform.
But if you're using Iceberg, your platform can look like this, right?
Specifically like Parquet doesn't matter so much.
But if you're using Iceberg, you have a whole range of catalogs you can use.
You can use the cuteness, you can use something else.
There's quite a few cute catalogs in the market, to be honest,
and then lots of query engines,
so you can really build the structure and the data platform that works for you.
Thanks to these open standards, you build them for performance.
You build them for cost, you build it for preference,
or you build it because that's you've moved to a new company
and that's what they're doing and they won't budge.
But really it's up to you.
You don't have to sacrifice performance by locking yourself in with someone.
And this is thanks to Apache Iceberg and specifically the Apache Iceberg Rest spec.
So this is how engines and catalogs talk to each other, basically.
So all these engines on the left can easily talk
out of the box to all these catalogs on the right, because they use the spec.
There's 1 or 2 caveats with some of the catalogs for there's
some sort of right issues in some of them, maybe around unity, a little bit
about Glue, but you have a lot of options and this is fantastic.
It really blows open the space to build things you want to do.
If you don't want to just buy a solution.
And it's really like in this
comic in action, the entire modern analytic space is propped up by this.
So even stuff like Fabric is using the Rest spec.
And now so is someone like Databricks, whose entire platform is built around
competing format Delta Lake.
So in summary, data analytics
and engineering have the same data needs, right?
Data has to be accessible.
So it needs to be widely available to everybody in your company, but
also safely through governance features such as RBAC, role based access control
and fine grained access control that you can put at every single level
from the bucket to the row needs to be understandable.
So you need rock solid, you know, definitions you agree on.
So you're not leaving people to interpret stuff
because that's when things go wrong and it needs to be performing.
So you query the data where it is, you're not moving it, you're not cleaning it,
and you're not waiting for stuff to read.
You're not at the most, you have some IOPs pains and all of this is delivered
a really performant technology which isn't tied to a specific vendor.
It's thanks to open standards, in particular, Arrow and Iceberg.
But there are others involved too.
Yeah.
So you're not locked into to anybody else, but you can actually deliver
the kind of infrastructure and data delivery and data quality
you need to send to your whatever you're engineering or analyzing.
That's it for me.
Thank you.
We have time for questions
if you want to do questions.
Since we talked about the data that
I have to ask the question here and there. Yes.
And my question, of course, is
a lot of data queries, especially the execution by agents
specifically, the scenario would be let's say that you have, let's say capital
calculations of thinking about it, nicely created formatted version of right one.
But then you also give the data primitives
that that are required to calculate, let's say the cap.
How do you prevent the AI from wasting time and tokens
and trying to do it from scratch, instead of using the right
to determine the right data path? Yes.
So part of the setup is you've got your tools and prompts and templates
to try and hem in performance or the kind of queries you do.
So ours is kind of focused on analytics in that space.
But in terms of MCP in general, the intent is it's more for builders, right?
You're building your own setup.
Bring whichever model you like to the table.
So implementation of guardrails and stuff like that.
It's more on the builders in particular.
So we give you discrete actions.
You can take in data sets you can access based on the credentials
you're accessing with.
But in terms of burning tokens
that's your problem as well I'm afraid.
But for the agent we have in the UI that's
that's limited more and we have a very clear spend for that.
And they should bring again, you bring your own agent for that.
But again we track we track the spend their.
Yes. Oh
sorry I was looking the wrong way.
I like to start with.
So one of the questions I have for you, if you look at what you have
on your platform, one of the things I'm interested in is in general contrast in.
It's kind of environment.
You've just got the NBA, but what I'm trying to understand is
how can you expose some of the functionality of the capability
so that you can stack so much of the data?
So one of the things that we're building
is the ability to have data agents you have tend to get across.
But one of the things we want to do is you have a bunch of suite domains on there
and you've got data range which accessing the data.
But it has to understand how
any of the data that's in there and protected data.
How do you respond to that so that the the agent
during the work and understand what the hell out works in that sense.
So I'm the let's say Claude is doing a query to the query.
And if it doesn't know anything about what it's doing,
it's going to have to figure it out.
How do you expose that data and how can you have it set that
layer that can then be wrong to use them?
Okay, well, the query engine is just the execution.
So in terms of our MCP, Claude would right, would connect
to that, understand the kind of actions it can take like execute SQL
analytics is, is is nice and simple in that regard.
Really you're writing SQL for a lot of stuff you're doing,
and the semantic layer provides the information it needs.
So it can search for schemas and keywords in what you're asking for.
And the semantic layer and vector search will help you find the right things.
And it's execute across against that.
But in terms of understanding a bit more specifically about what sort of
tools do as well, the CLI does similar, right?
You got you got the JSON structure comes back
and your agent or your model can understand what you can do
and what to expect from from certain actions and then act accordingly.
Yeah.
Because I'm just there's a, there's a missing piece of
if I'm running a small rebellion, I'm running a task which is accepting
data, composing a data, cleaning, looking at the data and then composing,
creating a data product, which is then fell into place,
where I'm trying to figure out is, how can you do that with what you have?
So I you saying you've got a bunch of MCP, bunch of endpoints.
Yeah.
And that's how you would do it.
So you have to construct yourself.
What you're saying is it's all there.
But you got to construct
there's no way there's no more intelligent way of exposing.
The infrastructure.
So you don't have to do the work that makes sense.
And the work you mean is creating a data product or understanding what's in the.
Self has to act as a way to data
that looks in the in the catalog.
At the moment
where you're describing it, and you have to do that.
You can composer from your endpoints.
So you have to work that out yourself and execute.
You don't mind pieces to work it out.
Well, it doesn't have to.
You ask it to do something.
It accesses through the semantic layer.
So the layering is a little.
Little skewed here really.
Everything goes through the semantic layer and it gets the context
and the understanding of your
the estate what data sets you have, what things are open to you as a user
and relates what you're asking to do to what's available.
It knows what actions to take because of MCP like it does.
You want to.
And how much you
do you have run into because of all the employees?
One of the things that we're working on is being able to have such
a scripture meditate to some of the aging consumer standard of this point.
Yeah,
yeah. So
it sounds like you'd be more interested
in a CLI kind of approach, which is more structured and detailed.
And the idea here is to give a workloads and multi-agent workflows stuff
where you don't want a person involved sort of overseeing and micromanaging.
You give it that, and that provides information in a way that's more cost
effective and efficient for an AI doing its own thing.
So yeah, looking to I can share some links about the CLI
if you like or that's that's the way I would do it.
It's better value for money and less work for you.
Yes. Sorry.
And then you.
How do you deal or do you have the machinery
access control and
how do you make something like an agent
even just for what they do, rules where it needs to because,
you know, there's all this uncertainty inherently.
So you can just go in and says something. Yes.
You got to give you a vote and get it back.
I work in genomics.
That's a big problem with this is just, you know, people can see that.
Those people cannot see that,
you know, because I want to do so you have that machinery or.
Yeah. Yeah.
So actually we work with Genomics England, the big customer of us.
And they're doing work using our platform.
But actually it's kind of basic.
So I mean, I mean, I said earlier, the AI semantic layer is
basically the semantic layer with fancy term on the front.
And the agent access is kind of also just repurposing stuff that's there.
Right?
It accesses through a user account like your user account.
So whether I'm querying information or masking agent to do it on my behalf,
it can see the same things through. Yeah,
yeah.
This guy in front was waiting longer.
You went to about the Open Semantic.
Interchange interchange.
I was wondering how it relates with semantic Web technologies
like from our
top of those and starting from scratch.
It's a I'm not too sure the answer.
I'm not too similar with the semantic web, but in terms of OSI.
So I talked about Arrow.
Actually, it's a good example app at the top.
And it makes always, always think about Arrow
when I think about it, because Arrow started out as a in-memory format
and then so they got every system using and sort of processing data in memory
the same way, but in getting it between the systems was a pain
because columns and system A, columns and system B,
you have to turn it to Rose to get across and back to columns.
So then the transport format came along and that was the next extension.
Whereas OSI, as far as I'm up to date, is the reverse.
So it's the idea of a standardized format to share information between systems.
And that's as far as it's really got.
So JSON is the main one at the moment.
There are issues of JSON. It's not very efficient.
I think more specs will come out or get more interesting,
but in terms of what it looks like when it's in system A and system B,
I don't think there's any any hard requirements on that.
It's just I think it really came out of trying to not vendor lock
your business context to a certain tool.
So I'll research the web and find out.
Yes.
In my experience in case.
When you support
like different data sources are like, let me quit all the data
and then you have the fun out like tens of different ways.
Unlimited groups. Yes.
Is there any tricks around, like kind of making the agents aware
of the latency of the queries so that they can be more
sophisticated about, okay, let me do the fast access first
and then do the federated calls like manually,
then offloading everything into the engine self.
They may be in some tools, I know, sort of higher end
sort of federation focused platforms do do stuff like that.
We don't so much.
Instead we have so that the basic approach is like, okay,
if you want it to be fast, create a table
in a data table, sort of linked copy
that you'll run from in your lake, and you get rid of the dependencies.
And also you get rid of
the sort of hammering the source system when you're running queries.
The more interesting thing the workaround we've done is reflections.
So this is a will.
Look at any queries you're running that are taking too long.
So this will include other systems.
And it makes materialized tables that will speed up those queries
and then sub them in.
So you can still keep say questioning your Hadoop system.
Say it takes a minute and a minute and eight seconds.
Something like that will make a table that gives you a better performance,
and it will sub it into your query without you having to change your SQL,
and that will get you to performance you want without messing around.
So quite a few of the sort of features we have and things are again are around
making the user experience and nicer for people who aren't technically minded.
So you can optimize hands on.
But for some people, like I don't want to.
Do you right to that.
No. It
just doesn't realize
that you're supposed to be.
You don't have to do anything.
Basically,
don't look at anything that runs too slow and it will speed up those queries
for you.
So you asked the same.
And then when when it's executing the query, the query panel will sub
in its other table and execute against that.
It tells you it's doing it, but you don't have to do anything around it.
I think that is.
Okay if you have no questions.
I'm sure the whole time after it.
Sure, yeah.
And I'm also around, so come get me.
Thank you.
Oh, no. Oh!